Inventory of the Maria Wolters papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Maria Wolters papers
1874-1959
41000
Wolters, Maria.
5 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection includes materials related to famine and earthquake relief and welfare in Japan, and consists of writings, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1941.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Herbert Hoover subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Stanley K. Hornbeck papers, Hoover Institution Archives
American National Red Cross records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Maria Wolters was a German-American relief worker in Japan from 1904 to 1959. She organized a fundraising drive in the U.S. that raised millions for farmers and victims of earthquakes. She also donated large sums out of her savings for child welfare in Japan.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers relate to the life of Wolters, documenting her fundraising campaign for relief efforts in Japan in 1904-1959. The collection includes some biographical information on Wolters, correspondence file, drafts and typescript of Wolters's memoir "The Power of Love," as well as other writings on her relief efforts in Japan. The papers contain a set of Relief work files with a variety of collected material such as "The Food-Blockade Petition Book," a scrapbook, financial records, and printed matter. In addition, the collection contains photographs depicting Wolters and her Japanese colleagues and friends.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
International relief.; Child welfare--Japan.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1874-1959 (Box 1)
  Includes identification documents, letters of reference, photographs, and Wolters's will.
  Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Identification documents, 1922-1936 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - References, 1882-1891 (Folder 1: 3-4)
  - Photographic prints of Wolters, her family, and friends, 1874-1956 (Folder 1: 5-11)
  - Will and testament, 1959 (Folder 1: 12)
    Includes drafts and copy of letter to Herbert Hoover
- Correspondence, 1903-1959 (Box 1-3)
  Arranged in two groups: General and alphabetical, the latter by name of person or organization
  - General, 1905-1958
    - 1903-1958 (Folder 1: 13-23, Folder 2: 1-7)
    - American schools, 1931-1936 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Japanese officials, circa 1918 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Japanese schools, 1918 (Folder 2: 10)
  - American Red Cross, 1927-1928 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Barkley, Alben W., 1949 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Board of Education, Los Angeles, 1934-1954 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Boy Scouts of America, 1932 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Brownell, H., 1933-1956 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Bruhn, Lucy, M., 1932-1933 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Chinese Foreign Famine Relief Committee, Shanghai, 1931-1936 (Folder 2: 17-18)
  - Consulate General of Japan, Los Angeles, 1952-1957 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Consulate General of Japan, New York, 1906-1911 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight, 1949-1957 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Haneda, Fujio, 1958-1959 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Herman, Raphael, 1935 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1927-1948 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Japanese Imperial Garden parties invitations, 1933-1936 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Kleinsorg, W. H., 1958-1959 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Martin, Bertha, 1903 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Ninagawa, Torazo, 1953 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1954-1957 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Osbourn, Rae, 1958 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Rickard, Edgar, 1940-1948 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin, 1937 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Roseboro, Viola, 1932-1936 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Stanford University, 1941-1959 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Suzuki, Hidesaburo, 1926-1956 (Folder 3: 8-10)
  - Takeo, T., 1908-1958 (Folder 3: 11-12)
- Writings, 1903-1959 (Box 3-4)
  Consists of appeals, petitions, poems, and books
  Arranged chronologically except for the memoir, which is at the end
  - Appeals, petitions, poems, and notes, 1903-1959 (Folder 3: 13-22)
  - "The Power of Love," memoir, 1950 (Folder 4: 1-5)
    Includes manuscript, typescript, and binder's copy
- Relief Work Files, 1904-1959 (Box 4-5)
  Contains correspondence, contacts, financial documents, printed matter, scrapbooks, and clippings
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Contacts, circa 1950 (Folder 4: 6-9)
  - Financial documents, 1904-1959 (Folder 4: 10, Folder 5: 1-4)
    Includes statements from the Maria Wolters Fund, receipts from charities, and daily expenses notebooks
  - "Food-Blockade Petition Book," a scrapbook by people who sighed the petition for the abolishment of a war time food blockade, 1928-1941 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Red Cross decoration, 1926 (Folder 5: 6)
    See also Memorabilia
  - School Boys' and Girls' World Friendship League, 1925-1957 (Folder 5: 7-11)
    Includes appeals, correspondence, writings, printed matter, clippings, and lists of committee members
  - Miscellany, circa 1950 (Folder 5: 12-13)
    Includes printed matter, clippings, and notes
- Memorabilia, 1920-1950 (Box 6)
  Handmade appreciation gifts, memorial coins collection, and jewelry box
  - Handmade appreciation gifts from Japan, circa 1950 (Folder 6)
  - Deutsches Rotes Kreuz medal with ribbon, 1926 (Folder 6)
  - German and Austrian World War I Commemorative coins, circa 1920 (Folder 6)
    Includes list of coins
  - Jewelry box, circa 1950 (Folder 6)